AMY GOODMAN: As we continue to talk about
the latest shake-up in the Trump administration,
let’s bring into this conversation former
CIA officer John Kiriakou, who personally
knew CIA director nominee Gina Haspel when
he worked at the CIA.
But their careers have taken very different
paths over the past decade.
Haspel, who was directly involved in torture
at a secret CIA prison in Thailand, has been
promoted to now head the agency.
Kiriakou, who blew the whistle on the torture
program, ended up being jailed for almost
two years.
John Kiriakou, welcome back to Democracy Now!
Can you respond to President Trump’s decision
to fire Rex Tillerson and replace Tillerson
with Pompeo as secretary of state?
Pompeo, head of the CIA, would be then replaced
by the deputy director of the CIA, Gina Haspel.
JOHN KIRIAKOU: Well, so many of us believed
a year ago that Rex Tillerson was going to
be the adult in the room at the White House.
That turned out to be the case, in a way,
but he was so disrespected by this president
and those around him that he was probably
doomed from the beginning.
On Mike Pompeo, I’ve said from the beginning,
you can disagree with him politically and
ideologically, but he doesn’t have the kind
of baggage that Gina Haspel has.
I wouldn’t have chosen Mike Pompeo to be
the secretary of state, but, I guess, in the
greater scheme of things, we could have done
worse.
Gina Haspel, however, is a problem, a big
problem.
I’ve been talking about Gina Haspel for
more than a year.
She was a dreadful choice to be the deputy
director.
She’s a worse choice to be the director.
I think it’s wonderful that there’s a
possibility of a woman heading the CIA, but
there are 50 different women who are qualified
to lead the CIA.
It shouldn’t be Gina Haspel.
AMY GOODMAN: So talk about why you and others
called her “Bloody Gina.”
JOHN KIRIAKOU: We did call her Bloody Gina.
Gina was always very quick and very willing
to use force.
You know, there was a group of officers in
the CIA’s Counterterrorism Center, when
I was—when I was serving there, who—I
hate to even make the accusation out loud,
but I’m going to say it: who enjoyed using
force.
Yeah, everybody knew that torture didn’t
work.
That’s not even the issue.
Lots of different things work.
Was it moral, and was it ethical, and was
it legal?
I think the answers to those questions are
very clearly no.
But Gina and people like Gina did it, I think,
because they enjoyed doing it.
They tortured just for the sake of torture,
not for the sake of gathering information.
AMY GOODMAN: And can you talk more specifically
about Gina Haspel heading up this secret CIA
black site in Thailand and—for those who
aren’t familiar with even what a black site
is—and the fact that she not only headed
it up, but was directly involved with the
torture?
JOHN KIRIAKOU: First, let me preface any comments
that I make by saying that the CIA’s Publications
Review Board is specifically prohibiting me
from talking about Gina Haspel’s résumé,
especially her overseas duty.
With that said, the media has reported extensively
on what Gina Haspel has done over the course
of her career, so I’ll leave it at that.
With that said, a black site is a site that’s
more or less off the books, meaning it doesn’t
officially exist.
It exists, but nobody is supposed to know
that it exists.
And in many cases, that includes the congressional
oversight committees.
So, in the immediate aftermath of 9/11, the
CIA set up such black sites all around the
world, with the idea being that if we captured
someone from al-Qaeda or kidnapped someone
from al-Qaeda, we could send him to one of
these black sites, interrogate him without
having to worry about the law, about ethics
or morality or the FBI breathing down their
backs.
They could do whatever they wanted.
And that’s how this torture program spiraled
out of control.
There were people who were murdered in the
course of their interrogations.